Guide to the Henry Miller Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry Miller Papers
1898-1979
1930-1979
YCAL MSS 472
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.29
(14 boxes)
The Henry Miller papers contain writings, journals, administrative files, correspondence, photographs, and personal papers chiefly documenting Miller's life and career from the 1950s through 1970s.
Miller, Henry, 1891-1980
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from PBA Galleries sale, San Francisco, 2010 March 18, lots 94-214 on the Edwin J. Beinecke and Alfred Z. Baker, Jr. funds, 2010.
From the collection of Roger Wagner.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Henry Miller Papers (Collection Number 110). Department of Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Henry Miller (1891-1980)
Henry Miller was a prolific and controversial Twentieth century author and painter. There are several book-length biographical studies of Miller, beginning with Alfred Perlès' My Friend, Henry Miller (1956), and including works by Jay Martin (1978), Mary Dearborn (1991), Béatrice Commengé (1991), and Judson Crews (1997), among others. Summary information on Miller is available in print and online biographical resources.
The following chronology provides key events and publications taken from Miller's My Life and Times (1971).
1891 Born in Yorksville section of Manhattan, New York, December 26th. Moved to Brooklyn.
1892-1900 Lived in Williamsburg, Brooklyn.
1901 Moved to Decatur Street in the Bushwick section of Brooklyn.
1909 Entered City College of New York and left after two months. Took a job with Atlas Portland Cement Company, New York.
1910 Began affair with Pauline Chouteau.
1913 Traveled through the West. Worked as a ranch hand. Met Emma Goldman.
1914 Back in New York, worked with father in his tailor shop. Met Frank Harris.
1917 Married Beatrice Sylvas Wickens of Brooklyn.
1919 Daughter Barbara Sylvas born.
1920 Worked as a messenger for several months, then became employment manager of messenger department, Western Union, New York.
1922 Wrote Clipped Wings during vacation from Western Union.
1923 Fell in love with dancer June Edith Smith.
1924 Left Western Union to devote energy to writing. Divorced Beatrice and married June Smith.
1925 Began writing career in earnest.
1927 Opened a speak-easy with June in Greenwich Village. While working for Park Department, Queens, compiled notes for autobiographical cycle of novels. Exhibited water colors in June Mansfield's roman Tavern, Greenwich Village.
1928 Toured Europe with June.
1929 Returned to New York. Completed This Gentile World.
1930 Returned to Europe alone, taking manuscript of another novel, lost by Edward Titus, editor of This Quarter, Paris.
1931-1932 Met Anaïs Nin. Began writing Tropic of Cancer. Worked as proof-reader on the Paris edition of the Chicago Tribune. Taught English at Lycee Carnot (Dijon).
1933. Took apartment with Alfred Perlès in Clichy and visited Luxembourg.
1934 Tropic of Cancer published. Divorced from June in Mexico City by proxy.
1935 Aller Retour New York published. First edition of Alf Letter appeared.
1936 Visited New York again. Black Spring published.
1937 Scenario published. Began publication of The Booster and Delta with Alfred Perlès.
1938 Began writing for French revue, Volontés. Money and How It Gets That Way published. Second edition of Alf appeared.
1939 Tropic of Capricorn and Hamlet published. Travelled in southern France and Greece.
1940 Returned to the U.S. Wrote The Colossus of Maroussi, The World of Sex, and Quiet Days in Clichy and began The Rosy Crucifixion.
1941 Travelled U.S. from October 1940 to October 1941.
1942 Left for California. Continued work on The Rosy Crucifixion and The Air-Conditioned Nightmare.
1943 Made 200-300 watercolors and exhibited at Beverly Glen (The Green House), American Contemporary Gallery, Hollywood.
1944 Married Janina Lepska in Denver, Colorado, December 18, 1944. Moved to Big Sur.
1945 Finished Sexus. Started translation of Season in Hell. Daughter Valentine born November 19.
1946 Moved to shack at Anderson Creek. Began work on Into the Night Life and The Time of the Assassins.
1947 Finished Into the Nightlife and began writing Plexus.
1948 Wrote The Smile at the Foot of the Ladder. Son Tony born August 28.
1949 Finished Plexus and began writing The Books in My Life.
1951 Finished The Books in My Life.
1952 Began writing Nexus. Divorced Janina Lepska.
1953 Spent time in England and France. Married Eve McClure in Carmel Highlands in December.
1954 Began writing Big Sur and the Oranges of Hieronymus Bosch.
1955 Saw daughter Barbara Sandford for first time since 1925.
1956 Recorded Henry Miller Recalls and Reflects. Collection of short pieces translated and published in Hebrew as Hatzoth Vahtzi (Half Past Midnight). Finished Big Sur and the Oranges of Hieronymus Bosch.
1957 Rewrote Quiet Days in Clichy and The World of Sex. Exhibitions of watercolors in London, Jerusalem, and Tel Aviv. Began writing Lime Twigs and Treachery.
1958 Continued work on Nexus.
1959 Finished Nexus. Spent time in Europe. Wrote letters contained in Art and Outrage.
1960 Wrote To Paint is to Love Again. Spent time in Europe. Wrote first draft of Just Wild About Harry.
1961 Toured Germany, Austria, Switzerland, Italy, Portugal and Spain. Tropic of Cancer published.
1962 Began writing volume two of Nexus. Spent time in England, Ireland, France, Germany. Received final decree of divorce from Eve.
1963 Moved to Pacific Palisades. Just Wild About Harry published.
1964 Henry Miller on Writing published.
1965 Death of Eve (third wife). Production of the opera The Smile at the Foot of the Ladder in Hamburg, Germany. Selected Prose and Letters to Anaïs Nin published.
1966 Order and Chaos Chez Hans Reichel published.
1967 The Smile at the Foot of the Ladder produced in Marseilles and Trieste. The Henry Miller Odyssey film begun by Robert Snyder. Married Hoki Tokuda on September 10.
1968 Watercolor exhibit toured Japan. Collector's Quest and new edition of To Paint is to Love Again published. Began writing My Life and Times.
1969 Premiere of The Henry Miller Odyssey at Royce Hall, U.C.L.A. Travelled to Europe to observe filming on Tropic of Cancer.
1970 Tropic of Cancer and Quiet Days in Clichy films opened in U.S. Insomnia or the Devil at Large and Entretiens de Paris published.
1971 My Life and Times published.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Miller papers contain writings, journals, administrative files, correspondence, photographs, and personal papers chiefly documenting Miller's life and career from the 1950s through 1970s, though the papers include significant items dating from the 1930s and earlier. Writings in the collection consist of drafts of shorter works dating from the 1970s, with biographical works on friends, family, and acquaintances, and material relating to earlier, well-known titles. There is a typescript carbon draft of Miller's Tropic of Capricorn, circa 1934, possibly the earliest surviving draft of this novel, and there are notes and proofs dating from the mid 1940s for Nexus, The Rosy Crucifixion, and The World of Sex. Miller's three Paris journals, dating from 1930s, include reflections on life in Paris, discussions on contemporary literature and art, excerpts from his major works of the period, and lists recording residences, places to visit, and other activities. Administrative files contain correspondence and financial and legal records relating to theatrical and cinematic productions of Miller's literary works during the 1960s and 1970s. Miller's correspondence from the 1960s and 1970s includes letters from friends, farmily, writers and artists, translators, and literary agents and publishers. In addition to files for Agence Hoffman, Grove Press, and Laurence Pollinger Ltd., there are letters from Lawrence Durrell, Erica Jong, Norman Mailer, Anaïs Nin, and Isaac Bashevis Singer. Other materials include photographs and personal papers such as address books, manuscript notes, and printed ephemera.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Writings, 1945-1979. II. Notebooks, 1930-1951. III. Administrative Files, 1962-1976. IV. Correspondence, 1928-1979. V. Photographs, 1910-1975. VI. Personal Papers, 1898-1978.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors; Durrell, Lawrence, 1912-1990; Jong, Erica, 1940-; Mailer, Norman, 1923-2007; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Nin, Anaïs, 1903-1977; Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1904-1991; Agence Hoffman; Grove Press; Laurence Pollinger Ltd; University of California, Los Angeles. Library
- Writings, 1968-1979; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Writings contains drafts, mostly corrected, of writings by Miller. The series consists chiefly of shorter works dating from the 1970s, with many biographical works on friends, family, and acquaintances, but also contains drafts for early and well-known titles. There is a typescript carbon draft of Tropic of Capricorn inscribed "First draft scrapped. Begun in Clichy 1934," possibly the earliest surviving draft of this novel; a heavily corrected proof of The World of Sex, dating from 1946; holograph synopsis and notes, dating circa the mid 1940s, outlining plots and characters for Nexus; and holograph notes, again dating from the mid 1940s, for The Rosy Crucifixion.
  - "Anaïs Nin: Venus Anadyomene," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1945-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence and printed ephemera
  - "At the Garden Door," song lyrics, typescript, corrected, 1968 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Bezalel Schatz," drafts, holograph and typescript, [circa 1977] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Books in My Life, drafts, incomplete, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - "Censorship," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1977 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Cousin Henry," draft, typescript, corrected, and typescript carbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Early Days in Williamsburg," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, and printed version, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Emile White," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Fuck Away, Fuck Away!" poem, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Introduction to 'Life and Times of H.M.'," drafts, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Je suis pas plus con qu'un autre!" drafts, holograph, photocopy, and typescript, corrected, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Jimmy Pasta," draft, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Joe Gray," drafts, holograph and typescript, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Marie Corelli," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Masculine=Feminine," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, [1972] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Max Winthrop," drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Miriam Painter," drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Mon Ami Alfred Perlès," notes and drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, [1979] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mother, I Love You, drafts, holograph and typescript photocopy, 1976 August 19 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - My Life and Times, "Henry Miller--Chronology," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "The Mystery of Japanese Women," draft, holograph, corrected, [1977] (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Nexus, synopsis and notes, holograph, [circa 1945-1950s] (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Nexus Vol 2," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, 1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-29)
  - "On Female Sexuality," draft, typescript carbon, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Includes letter to Miller from Mademoiselle
  - "On Seeing Jack Nicholson for the First Time," drafts, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
    Includes photographs and printed ephemera relating to the film "Five Easy Pieces"
  - "On Turning Eighty," draft, typescript carbon, [circa 1971] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Pauline," memoir, draft, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Plexus, corrections, typescript carbon, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - The Rosy Crucifixion, notes, holograph, [circa 1945] (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "Shlock or Literature?" review, draft, holograph, and printed version, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Includes letter from Miller to editor of Los Angeles Times
  - "Some Other Women in My Life," drafts, holograph and typescript, [1977] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - "The Theatre," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - "Things Are Getting Better," drafts, holograph, corrected, and typescript carbon, [1976] (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - "The Third Eye," draft, typescript, corrected, 1957 August 19 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Includes correspondence with "T. Lobsang Rampa" and clippings
  - "To the Editor of the L.A. Times," letter, draft, holograph, corrected, and typescript carbon, 1976 February 14 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Tropic of Capricorn, draft, typescript carbon, bound and with case, [1934?] (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
  - Tropic of Capricorn, preface, revised translation, 1972 January 29 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - The World of Sex, proof, corrected, 1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 46-47)
    Includes photographs
  - Untitled one-act play, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Notebooks, 1930-1951; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series II. Notebooks consists of several notebooks dating from 1930 to 1951.
  Series II. features Miller's three Paris journals, dating from 1930 to 1936, containing notes and writings in English and French, as well as artwork, letters, photographs, and printed ephemera. Miller's notes and writings document his life in Paris during what was also an important period in his literary development. They include his reflections on life in Paris, discussions on contemporary literature and art, "specimen" pages and excerpts from his major works of the period, Tropic of Cancer (1934), Black Spring (1936), and Tropic of Capricorn (1939), and from the work of others. There are also many lists, for example, Miller's residences in Paris, places to visit, titles for chapters and books, names of characters, books to read, agendas, and translations from the French.
  The Paris notebooks also contain the following: letters from Jean Cocteau, Paul Morand, Miller's father, William Aspenwall Bradley, and others; photographs of Miller, Anaïs Nin, and others; clippings of articles by Alfred Perlès and cartoons; and several sketches and watercolors.
  Other notebooks include notes and watercolors by Miller dating from 1937 to 1939 and many additional lists of where he sent manuscripts, things to do, people to see, pieces to write, and more.
  - Paris notebooks ("Notes [I-III] Paris"), 1930-[1936?] (Box 4, Folder 49-51)
  - Other notebooks, 1937-1951, undated (Box 5, Folder 52-54)
- Administrative Files, 1962-1976; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by production title.
  Series III. Administrative Files contains files relating to theatrical and cinematic productions of Miller's literary works during the 1960s and 1970s. Files contain financial records, legal records, correspondence, and other material. There are files for the play Just Wild About Harry, performed in France in 1978, and for the films Quiet Days in Clichy (1970) and Tropic of Cancer (1970). The correspondence consists chiefly of letters with representatives of law firms, publishers, literary agencies, and film production and distribution companies, though there are also letters from film directors Jen Jorgen Thorsen ( Quiet Days in Clichy ) and Joseph Strick ( Tropic of Cancer ) and some copies of letters from Miller. Other materials include publicity, reviews, and photographs.
  - Just Wild About Harry, 1967-1977 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    Includes photograph and printed ephemera
  - Quiet Days in Clichy, 1968-1975 (Box 5, Folder 56-58)
  - Tropic of Cancer, 1962-1971 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Tropic of Cancer, 1962-1971 (Box 6, Folder 60-63)
- Correspondence, 1928-1979; Series IV; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Series IV. Correspondence contains Miller's correspondence from the 1960s and 1970s. There are letters from friends, family, writers and artists, translators, and literary agents and publishers. In addition to larger files for Agence Hoffman, Grove Press, and Laurence Pollinger Ltd., there are letters from Lawrence Durrell, Erica Jong, Norman Mailer, Anaïs Nin, and Isaac Bashevis Singer.
  In 1978 Miller solicited support for the Nobel Prize for Literature. The Nobel Prize file contains a draft of Miller's letter to others, lists of "people to solicit," and responses, many enclosing copies of letters to the award committee in support of Miller's candidacy. There are letters from a wide mix of supporters inside and outside of the United States, including writers and translators, friends, editors and publishers, artists and gallery owners, filmmakers and other cultural figures, literary scholars, lawyers, and politicians. Correspondents include Kay Boyle, Christian de Bartillat, Hayashi Shiro, Joseph Strick, Grove Press, and Georg Stefan Troller, among others.
  Correspondence with law firms, literary agents, publishers, and film production and distribution companies can also be found in Series III. Administrative Files.
  - Agence Hoffman ("contracts"), 1961-1977 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Agence Hoffman, 1961-1966 (Box 6, Folder 65-68)
  - Agence Hoffman, 1967-1979 (Box 7, Folder 69-76)
  - Corbett, June ("Miller"), 1965-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Durrell, Lawrence, undated (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Fonda, Jane, 1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Grove Press, 1969-1978 (Box 7, Folder 80-81)
    Includes financial and legal records
  - Houghton, Claude, [1942?], 1958 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Insley, Joseph J., 1978 (Box 8, Folder 83)
    Includes photograph
  - Jong, Erica, 1974-1978 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    Includes copies of poems
  - Laurence Pollinger Limited, 1963-1978 (Box 8, Folder 85-86)
  - Mailer, Norman, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Mann, Roderick, 1978 March 22 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Marceau, Marcel, 1973 March (Box 8, Folder 89)
    Includes drawings
  - Miller, Eve McClure (4th wife), 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Miller, Janina Lepska (3rd wife), 1972 July (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Nin, Anaïs, 1966-1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Nobel Prize for Literature file, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 93-96)
  - Pasta, James, 1974-1979 (Box 8, Folder 97)
    Includes printed ephemera
  - Perlès, Alfred, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 98)
    Includes photograph of Perlès and woman
  - Pole, Rupert, 1965, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Rampa, Lobsang T., 1957-1958
  - Reece Halsey Agency, 1974-1979, undated (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Schatz, Bezalel, 1973-1978, undated (Box 9, Folder 101-102)
  - Scott Meredith Literary Agency, 1974-1979, undated (Box 9, Folder 103-104)
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1978 September 7 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - Stettner, Irving, 1978 December 21 (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Tobita, Shigeo, 1968-1973 (Box 9, Folder 107-109)
  - Tokuda, Hoki, 1972 September 8 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Vecsey, Esther, 1962 March 15 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - [Warren, Robert], undated (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - White, Emil, 1975-1979 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Unidentified, 1928 August 26 (Box 9, Folder 114)
- Photographs, 1910-1975; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by name and/or subject.
  Series V. Photographs contains photographs of Miller, friends, "girlfriends," and family, as well as sites from Miller's childhood in Brooklyn. There is also an early photograph of Miller, dating from 1910, with members of the Xerxes Society.
  - Brooklyn, undated (Box 10, Folder 115)
    Includes sites from Miller's childhood
  - "Girlfriends", 1940-1975, undated (Box 10, Folder 116-121)
    Includes photographs of Miller
  - Miller, Eve McClure (wife), 1957-1965, undated (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Miller, Heinrich (father), 1916 December (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - Miller, Hoki Tokuda (wife), [1970s] (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - Nina, Anaïs, 1971, undated (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Perlès, Alfred, 194[4?]-1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Sandford, Barbara (daughter), [1920s]-1938, undated (Box 10, Folder 127)
  - Schatz, Bezalel
  - Xerxes Society, 1910-1912, undated (Box 10, Folder 128-129)
- Personal Papers, 1898-1978; Series VI; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series VI. Personal Papers includes various other personal items belonging to Miller, including address books, manuscript notes, and printed ephemera. The chronology found here in Series VI provides a more detailed account of events during the period from April 1959 to August 1963 than the chronology found in Series I, "Henry Miller--Chronology," from My Life and Times, which documents Miller's life from 1891 to 1971.
  - Address books, [circa 1960s] (Box 11, Folder 130-132)
  - Addresses (card file), undated (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Astrological information, 1966-1971, undated (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Audio recordings, 1956, 1962 (Box 135-136)
    Contains phonograph recordings of Henry Miller Recalls and Reflects (1956) and Just Wild About Harry (1962)
  - Bibliography, printed version, annotated by Miller, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - "East-West Blues: A New Yorker Comes West By Erica Jong," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - Handprints and analysis, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - "Henry Miller Chronology", 1963 (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - "Henry Miller manuscripts and related material deposited with the UCLA Library...", 1948-1978, undated (Box 13, Folder 141-143)
  - List of debts owed, undated (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - "Livre de femmes (Roster) de l'enfance a la veillesse et de partout au monde", undated (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - Manuscript notes, 1932
  - Material relating to marriage between Henry Miller and Hoki Tokuda, 1967-1977, undated (Box 13, Folder 146-147)
  - Membership certificate, National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 148)
  - Printed ephemera, 1957-1976, undated (Box 13, Folder 149-150)
  - Sketch book (with drawings), undated (Box 13, Folder 151)
  - Theater programs and publicity, 1898-1920s (Box 13, Folder 152-153)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - The Rosy Crucifixion, notes (In Series I), [circa 1945] (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - Notebook (In Series II), 1937-1951 (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - Clippings for Quiet Days in Clichy (In Series III), 1970, undated (Box 14, Folder 156)
  - Letter from Lawrence Durrell on printed broadside (In Series IV), undated (Box 14, Folder 157)
  - Royalty statements from Grove Press (In Series IV), 1978 (Box 14, Folder 158)
  - Manuscript notes (In Series VI), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 159)
  - Theater programs and publicity (In Series VI), 1898-1920s (Box 14, Folder 160)